Guide to the Luis Alberto Guajardo Collection of Músquiz, Mexico Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Luis Alberto Guajardo Collection of Músquiz, Mexico Records
1553-1889
1801-1889
WA MSS S-1482
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.09
(17 boxes)
The Luis Alberto Guajardo Collection of Músquiz, Mexico Records contains administrative records from the town of Músquiz, Coahuila, Mexico. The records were collected by Luis Alberto Guajardo, a general in the Mexican Army. Guajardo's military travels allowed him to visit local record offices in Coahuila and research the history of the region. This research led to the formulation of Guajardo's Apuntes Datos y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila, a history of the Coahuila region. The Records are arranged in five overlapping chronologies. This order has been maintained from an earlier, unknown processor, perhaps Guajardo himself. The chronologies include circulars issued by the Coahuila government; religious, legal, military, land, water, and mining records pertaining to Musquiz and the Coahuila region; census records, including the documentation of Indians, widows, slaves, and vassals; legal records, including records administering issues of violence against women; documents pertaining to the administration of Indian affairs, particularly those of the Seminole and Apache tribes; and indices of correspondence and decrees in Coahuila, wills, and court proceedings. Also included is material on the founding and history of the Texas region, as well as English language manuscript land petitions, citizenship records, and legal proceedings of Thomas Jefferson Chambers.
Guajardo, Luis Alberto
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles and Lindley Eberstadt, 1961.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated material: Luis Alberto Guajardo Papers on the History of Coahuila (WA MSS S-668). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The Luis Alberto Guajardo Collection of Músquiz, Mexico Records contains administrative records from the town of Músquiz, Coahuila, Mexico. The records were collected by Luis Alberto Guajardo, a general in the Mexican Army. Guajardo's military travels allowed him to visit local record offices in Coahuila to research the history of the region, collect documents, and make copies of original documents. This research led to the formulation of Guajardo's Apuntes Datos y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila, a history of the Coahuila region. Much of the material contained in this collection appears to have been used in the creation of the Apuntes Datos y Noticias.
The collection is arranged in five overlapping chronologies, apparently created by Guajardo. In some areas of this collection, his manuscript notes are present and indicate how he has grouped material.
The First Chronology is the largest and includes administrative records, particularly census records, land records, legal records, and records pertaining to the administration of Indian affairs.
The Second Chronology is very similar to the First Chronology and includes administrative records and circulars issued by the Coahuila government.
The Third Chronology includes religious, census, property, and legal records pertaining to Músquiz and the Coahuila region.
The Fourth Chronology contains administrative records for the Coahuila region, including census, land, and water records; census rolls, including rolls of Indian (particularly Seminole and Apache) residents; records pertaining to mining in the Santa Rosa region; an account of the founding of Piedras Negras; and records pertaining to the military budget.
The Fifth Chronology includes indices of correspondence and decrees in Coahuila, wills, and court proceedings. The land petitions, citizenship, and legal proceedings of Thomas Jefferson Chambers are especially well documented and include manuscripts in English. This chronology also includes material on the founding and history of the Texas region.
Luis Alberto Guajardo's Folders (now empty) consists of folders Guajardo used. When the collection was processed in 1993 these folders were empty, but the folders have been kept with the collection because they include Guajardo's notes and may provide information regarding how he organized the collection.
Biographical / Historical
Luis Alberto Guajardo (1872-1925) was a general in the Mexican Army. He was born in Músquiz, Coahuila and participated in the Mexican Revolution. His military travels allowed him to visit local record offices in Coahuila and research the history of the region, as well as make copies of original documents. This research led to the formulation of Apuntes Datos y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila, a history of the Coahuila region.
Indians of Mexico -- Mexico -- Coahuila and Texas; Indians of North America -- Southwest, New; Land grants -- Mexico -- Coahuila and Texas (Mexico); Land grants -- Texas; Mineral industries -- Mexico; Cattle trade -- Mexico; Apache Indians; Cholera -- Mexico; Comanche Indians; Public health -- Mexico -- Coahuila and Texas (Mexico); Seminole Indians; Women -- Mexico; Women -- Social conditions -- Mexico; Women -- Violence against -- Mexico; Coahuila and Texas (Mexico) -- Colonization; Coahuila and Texas (Mexico) -- Politics and government; Coahuila (Mexico: State); Mexico -- History -- 1821-1861; Mexico -- History -- To 1810; Músquiz (Mexico); Provincias Internas (New Spain); Texas -- History -- To 1846; Texas -- Emigration and immigration; Mining engineering -- Mexico; Mines and mineral resources -- Mexico; Chambers, Thomas Jefferson, 1802-1865; Guajardo, Luis Alberto
- First Chronology, Series I; 4.17; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged in chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  The material contained in this chronology primarily consists of administrative records, particularly census records and land records. Some of the documents are bound together and others show signs of having once been bound.
  Material contained within the First Chronology includes land grant petitions, particularly in the Santa Rosa Maria del Sacramento region; census records indicating widows, slaves, and vassals; records documenting the administration of legal matters pertaining to violence against women; records describing efforts to manage public health issues, particularly cholera and syphilis; and records pertaining to government management of Indian groups in the 18th and 19th centuries, particularly Apache groups.
  - 1740-1759 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes land grant petitions and administrative records issued by Pablo Mauricio de la Garza Falcon and Miguel de la Garza Falcon.
  - 1763-1765 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1766-1769 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1770-1775 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Will of José Gregorio Sanchez (probably labeled by Guajardo), 1775-1809 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1776-1779 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1780-1782 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1783-1784 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes census records and records of widows, slaves, and vassals.
  - 1785-1785 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes documents pertaining to the administration of Indian relations.
  - 1786-1787 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1788-1789 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1790-1792 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1793-1797 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1798-1800 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1802-1802 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1803-1803 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1804-1805 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1806-1806 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1807-1807 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1808-1808 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Includes census records.
  - 1809-1809 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1810-1810 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 1811-1812 June (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 1812 July-December (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - 1813-1813 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 1814-1814 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - 1815 January-March (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 1815 April-June (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - 1815 July-December (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - 1816 January-May (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - 1816 June-December (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - 1817 January-September (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - 1817 October-December (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - 1818-1818 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - 1819-1819 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - 1820 January-June (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - 1820 July-December (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - 1821 January-June (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - 1821 July-October (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - 1821 November-December (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - 1822 January-May (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Includes decrees of the Secretario de Estado y Relaciones Interiores y Exteriores, as well as material pertaining to mining in the Santa Rosa region.
  - 1822 June-December (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - 1823 January-April (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - 1823 May-December (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Includes a manuscript circular by the Ministerio de Relaciones Interiores y Exteriores
  - Part I of 1824 (probably labeled by Guajardo), 1824-1824 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Part II of 1824 (probably labeled by Guajardo), 1824-1824 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - 1825 January-February (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - 1825 March-May (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - 1825 June-July (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - 1825 September-December (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - 1826 January-March (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - 1826 April-June (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - 1826 July-August (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - 1826 September-December (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - 1827 January-April (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - 1827 May-July (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - 1827 August-December (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - 1828 January-March (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - 1828 April-June (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - 1828 July-December (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - 1829 January-March (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - 1829 April-August (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - 1829 September-December (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - 1830 January-June (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - 1830 July-August (Box 6, Folder 65)
    Includes descriptions of plans to prevent the spread of cholera.
  - 1830 September-December (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - 1831 January-May (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - 1831 June-September (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - 1831 October-December (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - 1832 January-September (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - 1833 January-May (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - 1833 June-December (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - 1834 January-February (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - 1834 March-April (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - 1834 May-December (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - 1835 January-February (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - 1835 March-December (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - 1836 January (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - 1836 February-June (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - 1836 July-August (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - 1836 September-December (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - 1837 January-May (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - 1837 July-December (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - 1838-1839 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - 1840-1840 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - 1841 January-May (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - 1841 June (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - 1841 August-December (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - 1842-1844 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - 1845-1847 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - 1851-1851 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - 1852 January-April (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - 1852 May-August (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - 1852 September-December (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - 1853 January-June (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - 1853 July-August (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - 1853 September-October (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - 1853 November-December (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - 1854 January-March (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - 1854 April-June (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - 1854 July-August (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - 1854 September-December (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - 1855 January-April (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - 1855 May-September (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - 1855 October-December (Box 9, Folder 105)
  - 1856 January-April (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - 1856 May-June (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - 1856 July-December (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - 1857-1857 (Box 10, Folder 109)
    Includes descriptions of abuse against women, including domestic violence and keeping a concubine, and the associated fines levied by municipal authorities against perpetrators.
  - 1858 January-March (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - 1858 April-June (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - 1858 July-August (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - 1858 September-October (Box 10, Folder 113)
    Includes testimonies of domestic violence and sexual assault.
  - 1858 November (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - 1858 December (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - 1859 January-March (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - 1859 April-May (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - 1859 June-September (Box 10, Folder 118)
    Includes descriptions of efforts to remove a servant and a syphilitic American due to their infection with the disease and rumors of filibusterers gathering on the Rio Grande.
  - 1859 October-December (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - 1860-1860 (Box 10, Folder 120)
    Includes a description of a dispute over a doctor failing to report a contagious disease in Músquiz.
  - 1861-1861 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - 1862-1862 (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - 1865-1865 (Box 10, Folder 123)
- Second Chronology, Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  The Second Chronology is very similar to the first and includes administrative records and circulars issued by the Coahuila government. Many of the documents in this chronology pertain to municipal budgetary matters; the budget of the city of Músquiz; municipal government sessions; the Mexican army, particularly the Ejercito del Norte; and the enforcement of the Catholic faith in the country. Some documents have been numbered, some are bound, and many show signs of having once been sewn together.
  - 1851-1851 (Box 11, Folder 124)
    Includes circulars pertaining to the government budget of Músquiz
  - 1852-1852 (Box 11, Folder 125)
    Includes records of governmental sessions
  - 1853-1853 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - 1854-1854 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - 1855-1855 (Box 11, Folder 128)
    Includes documents pertaining to the government budget of Músquiz
  - 1856-1856 (Box 11, Folder 129)
    Includes documents pertaining to the Ejército del Norte
  - Part I of 1857, 1857-1857 (Box 11, Folder 130)
  - Part II of 1857, 1857-1857 (Box 11, Folder 131)
  - 1858-1858 (Box 11, Folder 132)
    Includes material pertaining to the administration of Indian affairs and the Fuerza del Canton
  - 1859-1859 (Box 11, Folder 133)
    Includes material pertaining to religious administration and enforcement
  - Part I of 1860, 1860-1860 (Box 11, Folder 134)
  - Part II of 1860, 1860-1860 (Box 11, Folder 135)
  - 1863-1863 (Box 11, Folder 136)
  - 1865-1865 (Box 11, Folder 137)
- Third Chronology, Series III; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The Third Chronology includes religious, census, property, and legal records pertaining to Músquiz and the Coahuila region. Local registers of citizens, including Indians, are included in this chronology, as are legal hereditary records, commerce records for the region, government correspondence records, and records about mining in the Santa Rosa region. The chronology consists primarily of bound manuscripts; many of these items are accompanied by notes in Guajardo's hand.
  - 1553-1594 (Box 12, Folder 138)
    Includes church, census, and property records
  - 1752-1819 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - 1752-1841 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - 1773-1814 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - 1783-1783 (Box 12, Folder 142)
  - 1786-1786 (Box 12, Folder 143)
  - 1786-1832 (Box 12, Folder 144)
  - 1798-1831 (Box 12, Folder 145)
  - 1803-1808 (Box 12, Folder 146)
    Includes documents pertaining to the administration of religion
  - 1805-1843 (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - 1806-1830 (Box 13, Folder 148)
    Includes records pertaining to the administration of Indian affairs, as well as local registers of citizens
  - 1807-1819 (Box 13, Folder 149)
  - 1809-1837 (Box 13, Folder 150)
  - 1814-1833 (Box 13, Folder 151)
  - 1814-1814 (Box 13, Folder 152)
  - 1817-1826 (Box 13, Folder 153)
  - 1820-1820 (Box 13, Folder 154)
  - 1822-1832 (Box 13, Folder 155)
    Includes records pertaining to commerce in the region
  - 1828-1849 (Box 13, Folder 156)
  - 1829-1834 (Box 13, Folder 157)
  - 1830-1830 (Box 13, Folder 158)
  - 1828-1836 (Box 13, Folder 159)
    Includes records pertaining to mining in the Santa Rosa region
  - 1833-1833 (Box 13, Folder 160)
  - 1834-1835 (Box 13, Folder 161)
  - 1840-1840 (Box 13, Folder 162)
  - 1845-1845 (Box 13, Folder 163)
  - 1847-1861 (Box 13, Folder 164)
- Fourth Chronology, Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged in chronological order by units of documents grouped by Luis Alberto Guajardo.
  The Fourth Chronology contains administrative records for the Coahuila region, including census, land, and water records; census rolls, including registers of Indian residents; records pertaining to mining in the Santa Rosa region; an account of the founding of Piedras Negras; and records pertaining to the military budget. Throughout this chronology there are autograph notes in the hand of Luis Alberto Guajardo that indicate that these records were being used in the formation of Apuntes Datos y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila.
  - 1676-1677 (Box 14, Folder 165)
  - 1699-1699 (Box 14, Folder 166)
    Includes land and census records
  - 1746-1779 (Box 14, Folder 167)
  - 1752-1786 (Box 14, Folder 168)
  - 1756-1756 (Box 14, Folder 169)
  - 1768-1768 (Box 14, Folder 170)
  - 1787-1787 (Box 14, Folder 171)
  - 1781-1788 (Box 14, Folder 172)
  - 1786-1826 (Box 14, Folder 173)
    Includes census rolls and records pertaining to Indians in the region
  - 1790-1799 (Box 14, Folder 174)
  - 1801-1806 (Box 14, Folder 175)
  - 1807-1808 (Box 14, Folder 176)
  - 1809-1819 (Box 14, Folder 177)
  - 1820-1828 (Box 14, Folder 178)
  - 1829-1830 (Box 14, Folder 179)
    Includes documents pertaining to mining in the Santa Rosa region
  - 1830-1831 (Box 14, Folder 180)
  - 1831-1833 (Box 15, Folder 181)
  - 1834-1840 (Box 15, Folder 182)
  - 1836-1836 (Box 15, Folder 183)
  - 1841-1841 (Box 15, Folder 184)
  - 1848-1848 (Box 15, Folder 185)
  - 1849-1849 (Box 15, Folder 186)
  - 1851-1852 (Box 15, Folder 187)
    Includes material pertaining to the founding of Piedras Negras
  - 1854-1859 (Box 15, Folder 188)
  - 1860-1860 (Box 15, Folder 189)
    Includes material pertaining to the administration of Indian affairs
  - 1860-1865 (Box 15, Folder 190)
    Includes military budget records and records pertaining to mining in the Santa Rosa region
  - 1886-1889 (Box 15, Folder 191)
- Fifth Chronology, Series V; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The Fifth chronology includes indices of correspondence and decrees in Coahuila, wills, and court proceedings. The land petitions, citizenship, and legal proceedings of Thomas Jefferson Chambers are especially well documented and include manuscripts in English. This chronology also includes material on the founding and history of the Texas region.
  Throughout this section there are autograph notes in the hand of Luis A. Guajardo suggesting an an order he imposed while creating Apuntes Datos y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila. Some of the folders were labeled by an unknown earlier processor and those titles have been maintained. Titles in brackets were provided in the summer of 1993.
  - [Indices of correspondence from the governor of Coahuila (bound)], 1763-1835 (Box 15, Folder 192)
  - [Instructions on Dr. Jayme Gurza's work at the Santa Rosa Military Hospital (typed and bound)], 1796-1840 (Box 15, Folder 193)
  - [Original will of T. Melechon Sanchez Nararro (bound)], 1804-1805 (Box 15, Folder 194)
  - [Court blotters], 1812-1824, 1843-1844 (Box 15, Folder 195)
  - [Transcript of court proceedings regarding a robbery], 1824-1824 (Box 16, Folder 196)
  - [Indices of decrees and orders issued by the governor of Santa Rosa], 1844-1854 (Box 16, Folder 197)
  - Thomas Jefferson Chambers made citizen of Mexico, 1830 February 28 (Box 16, Folder 198)
  - Deed of land in Mexico for Shadrach Bumly, 1830 April 10 (Box 16, Folder 199)
  - Mexican land grant to Thomas Jefferson Chambers, 1831 June 13 (Box 16, Folder 200)
  - Translated typescript copy of testimonies of title of T.J. Chambers, 1834 July 24 (Box 16, Folder 201)
  - Letter from T. J. Chambers to the judge in the first instance of the municipality of Austin regarding the political situation between Mexico and Texas, 1834 October (Box 16, Folder 202)
  - Description of the Chamber Jury Law of 1834, 1834-1834 (Box 16, Folder 203)
  - List of script to be issued by T.J. Chambers, 1836-1836 (Box 16, Folder 204)
  - Report to the General Council of the Provisional Government of Texas regarding raising an Army for the "protection of the liberties of Texas", 1836 January 7 (Box 16, Folder 205)
  - Names of tracts and amounts taken from Chambers by the Republic of Texas, 1838-1858 (Box 16, Folder 206)
  - Fernando de Leon versus S.A. White, 1848-1848 (Box 16, Folder 207)
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Pryor Lea to T.J. Chambers, 1856-1856 (Box 16, Folder 208)
  - Robert's sketch of T.J. Chambers, 1859-1859 (Box 16, Folder 209)
  - Part I of Chambers versus Shaw, 1859-1859 (Box 16, Folder 210)
  - Part II of Chambers versus Shaw, 1859-1859 (Box 16, Folder 211)
  - List of taxable property of T.J. Chambers, 1859-1859 (Box 16, Folder 212)
  - Autograph letter, signed, from Chambers to his nephew, 1862 February 12 (Box 16, Folder 213)
  - Printed memorials by children of T.J. Chambers, undated (Box 16, Folder 214)
  - Typescript report by Robert E. Cofer on the Chambers claim to the capital of Texas, undated (Box 16, Folder 215)
  - Manuscripts pertaining to the administration of Texas, 1784-1837 (Box 16, Folder 216)
  - Manuscripts pertaining to the administration of Texas, 1826-1865 (Box 16, Folder 217)
  - Unsorted material, 1846, undated (Box 16, Folder 218)
  - Unsorted material, 1834, undated (Box 16, Folder 219)
- Luis Alberto Guajardo's Folders (now empty), Series VI; 0.42; (1 box)
  These are folders used by Guajardo to house the material in the collection. Many of these folders include his manuscript notes. The folders were emptied by an unknown, earlier processor but have been kept with the collection in order to preserve his notes.
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 220)
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 221)
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 222)
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 223)
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 224)
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 225)
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 226)
  - Folders of Músquiz papers with handwritten comments (Box 17, Folder 227)